So when I ask what is ODO, what comes to
mind? Well, ODO is a bit of everything.
ODO is a suite of business management
software that some people say is like
fertilizer because of the way it
promotes growth. But you know, some
people also say ODU is like a magic bean
stock because it grows with your company
and is also magically affordable. But
then again, you could look at ODU in
terms of how its individual software
programs are a lot like building blocks.
I mean whatever your business needs,
manufacturing, accounting, HR programs,
you can build a custom software suite
that's perfect for your company. So what
is ODO? Well, I guess ODO is a bit of
everything. ODO is a fertilizer magic
beantock building blocks for business.
Yeah, that's it. Which means that ODO is
exactly what every business needs. Learn
more and sign up now at odo.com. That's
odo.com.
CIA is not supposed to collect any
information at all on American citizens
ever. They say that they don't. I want
to believe that they don't, but I really
don't
know. Okay. Thanks so much for joining
me. For all you true crime fans out
there, a new season of my podcast,
Mystery and Murder Analysis by Dr. Phil
is out. We have been gone for a little
while, but we are back bringing you some
really cuttingedge stories. My goal is
for every one of these stories to add
something to your understanding about
some of these monsters that walk among
us. The heartbreaking case of Gabby
Patito, whose life was tragically cut
short by her boyfriend Brian Laundry.
How could a pair living so-called
perfect lives be hiding such dark
secrets? Getting to know Gabby while
diving into the psychology of unhealthy
relationships. Were there red flags?
Mystery and murder analysis by Dr. Phil.
His promise of Till death do us part
seems pretty chilly. Available on Apple
Podcast and YouTube. You guys all
remember that story. You don't want to
miss this. Now, last week here on the
Dr. Phil podcast, I introduced you to
CIA torture whistleblower John Keryaku,
a former CIA counterterrorism officer
and senior investigator for the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee. Now, John
shared his incredible journey from his
early recruitment by the CIA to his rise
within the agency where he navigated the
ethical challenges posed by post 911
interrogation techniques. Now, known for
his bravery in exposing the CIA's use of
torture methods like
waterboarding, John became a
whistleblower, which led to his
indictment under the Espionage Act and
ultimately a 23month prison sentence.
But I said at the time, one episode
simply wasn't enough to cover
everything. John's experiences,
perspectives, and
advocacy left me, and I think all of you
wanting more.
and we knew we had to have him back to
dive deeper. So, in this part two of our
conversation, we'll uncover even more of
the untold truth behind his story and
the aftermath of his whistleblowing. So,
we're just going to jump right in. Was
there anything when we finished talking
that you felt like you wanted to say
more about particularly regarding the
whistleblowing? Well, there's one aspect
of it I think I'd like to talk about
just for a just for a moment. Uh we have
a whistleblower protection law in this
country called the Federal Whistleblower
Protection Act. But unfortunately,
national security whistleblowers are
exempt from its protections. And so if a
person who works for, let's say, the
CIA, the Pentagon, the FBI, DEA,
uh, one of the congressional um,
oversight committees, the intelligence
committees on Capitol Hill, if they want
to make a
revelation, there is no way to make a
protected revelation.
For example, we're told to go through
our chains of command, but if your chain
of command is what is violating the law,
there's really nowhere to go but the
media. And if you go to the media, of
course, you risk a criminal charge, you
risk bankruptcy, you risk your career,
everything. This is something that I
feel very strongly about that we need to
correct uh up on Capitol Hill. There
have to be protections implemented for
national security whistleblowers. So,
you're saying there's no accountability,
no way for anybody that's in those
services
to reach out for any kind of protection.
If you feel like things are happening
within the service that are illegal,
anti-American, anything at all that you
feel like should have oversight, there's
nowhere for you to go. There's nowhere
for you to go. And I'll give you an
example. Thomas Drake uh was a senior
member of the senior intelligence
service at uh NSA, the National Security
Administration uh National Security
Agency and um he found solid evidence of
um of illegality that is the
interception of communications of
American citizens without a warrant. So
he went to the inspector general. Uh the
inspector general was not read into the
compartment and so said he just didn't
know what Tom was talking about. He then
went to the general counsel. The general
counsel told him that this was above his
pay grade and he should just stop. So
then he went to the Pentagon inspector
general because NSA of course is a
component of the Pentagon. The Pentagon
inspector general told NSA, "Hey, you
have a rogue employee who came here to
complain about a program. didn't get any
satisfaction of course there. So he went
to the House Permanent Select Committee
on Intelligence and said NSA is
intercepting the communications of
American citizens. They charged him with
nine felonies, including seven counts of
espionage, two counts of theft of
government property, the property being
the information that he had in his brain
that he walked out of the building with.
um he was facing almost a hundred years
in prison and then the night before he
was to go to trial they dismissed the
charges but that was only after he had
lost his pension, lost his savings, lost
his wife, who was also an NSA employee
and decided to stay with NSA rather than
to stay with with Tom. Lost his five
children. He ended up working at an
Apple store as at the Genius Bar of an
Apple store in Bethesda,
Maryland. That's what happens when you
when you use the internal mechanisms
that have been set up for
whistleblowing, they just simply don't
work. So when you started on your
journey, where was the first place you
went?
I went to my boss and I said, "This is
wrong, wrong, wrong." And he said,
"Listen, this is way over our pay
grades. you need to keep your mouth
shut. And I actually did keep my mouth
shut for a long time. I resigned from
the CIA uh two years after uh after
learning of the the torture program
thinking that there were so many more
people more directly involved with it
than I who were objecting. You know, I
was seeing this reporting coming back
from the secret uh prison. Uh, for
example, physicians from the CIA's
Office of Medical Services saying,
"Whoa, wait a minute. I took a
hypocratic oath. I didn't sign up for
this to torture somebody." And then and
then do CPR on them just so he could be
tortured more. And I thought, well,
surely so many people are objecting that
somebody is going to say something to
stop this program. And then nobody did.
I'm ashamed to tell you that I let five
and a half years pass before I finally
said something. Did this continue during
that five and a half years?
It continued for four of those years
until 2006. And then in
2006, they just decided that what they
were getting from these these men under
torture wasn't amounting to anything.
And so they just shut it down. And who
made the decision to shut it down?
That was an internal CIA decision. So
George Tennant had left to the best of
my recollection by 2006 and it was uh
Porter Goss who finally came in. Porter
Goss had been not just a CIA officer but
he had then gotten himself elected to
Congress, became chairman of the House
Intelligence Committee, then went to the
CIA as the director and said, "Oh, this
this is not not what we should be
doing." Now, you were convicted under
the 1982 Intelligence Identities
Protection Act, right? Correct. And that
act says you were guilty of doing what?
I confirmed the surname of a former CIA
colleague to a to a a journalist. You
confirmed it, but the name was already
given. Correct. Yeah. Then the name was
out there. Um, I confirmed it to a
journalist, but the journalist never
made the name public. And and where my
attorneys objected in this whole process
was while I was defending myself uh from
this charge, the the director of the
CIA, General David Petraeus, confirmed
the names of 10 covert CIA officers uh
to his biographer and girlfriend and was
never charged.
Why do you think you were so selectively
prosecuted? Because as you say, there
were others, not just Petraeus, but
there were others that Right. Yes. did
much more than yourself. So why did they
come after you, Hammer and Tong? I had
aired the CIA's dirty laundry in public,
and that was something that to the CIA
was unforgivable. And I had one one
enemy in the CIA in particular uh and
that was John Brennan who later went on
to become the uh deputy national
security adviser in President Obama's
first term and then CIA director in the
second term. When when I was arrested,
the Justice Department turned over
15,000 pages of classified discovery and
we found three memos in that discovery.
One was a memo from John Brennan to Eric
Holder, the the attorney general at the
time, and he said, "Charge him with
espionage." And Holder wrote back and
said, "My people don't think he
committed espionage." And then Brennan
wrote back and said, "Charge him anyway
and make him defend himself." And so
that's what they did. And then when I
went bankrupt from from attorney's fees,
they dropped the espionage charges. When
my sleep was off, it felt like I
couldn't show up as my best self. That's
why I'm so excited to share something
that makes a real difference. Beam's
Dream Powder. Beam is proudly founded in
America and run by people who share our
values. hard work and integrity and
delivering results. It's a sciencebacked
healthy nighttime blend packed with
ingredients shown to improve sleep so
you can wake up refreshed and ready to
take on the day. Dream is made with a
powerful blend of all natural
ingredients. Rayi, magnesium, atheonine,
epigenine, and melatonin. Beam has
already improved over 17 1.5 million
nights of sleep, helping people across
the country wake up and feel their best.
Here's the deal. Beam is giving my
listeners the ultimate Patriot discount
of 40% off. Try their best-selling dream
powder and get up to 40% off for a
limited time. Go to
shopbeam.com/drill and use code drill at
checkout. That's
[Music]
shopbam.com/drfill and use code drill
for up to 40% off. Support an American
company. Invest in yourself and start
getting your best sleep
tonight. Life is full of surprises and
emergencies often strike when we least
expect them. But preparation is key and
that's where Jace Casease comes in.
With Jace Casease, you'll have essential
emergency prescription medications right
at your fingertips, ready when you need
them most. Whether it's an unexpected
illness or a travel mishap, having the
right meds on hand can turn a potential
crisis into just a minor inconvenience.
Don't let the unexpected catch you
offguard. Jace Casease gives you peace
of mind so you can tackle life surprises
with confidence.
Be ready. Take charge today. Head over
to jace.com. That's
jas.com and when you check out, use the
code phil spelled ph to get a discount
on your order and to have the right meds
on hand the moment you need them. Let's
see if I've got this right. You were
convicted under the 1982 Intelligence
Identities Protection Act, right? That's
right.
Did you plead guilty or were you
convicted? Oh, I plead guilty. Most
definitely. I asked my attorneys. I was
going to plead not guilty. And when I
say going to plead not guilty, I mean
the the Justice Department had made a a
best and final offer of 30 months. I do
23 months or we go to trial. My my wife
and I stayed up all night long the night
before uh just going through whatever
information we could about this
Intelligence Identities Protection Act.
And because nobody had ever challenged
it at trial, there was there was no
precedent. There were several articles
in the Harvard uh law journal saying
that it was
unconstitutional. And so I decided to
fight. So, I emailed my attorneys at six
o'clock in the morning and I said,
"Let's go to trial. We're going to
fight." And they emailed, one of them
emailed me back and said, "Put on a pot
of coffee. We're on the way over." So,
they came to the house at 7. The oldest
of my attorneys, the most experienced,
he had been an attorney in Washington
for 52 years, was what the Washington
Post called a legal titan, got right up
in my face and said, "You stupid sobb.
Take the deal." I said, 'Well, wait a
minute. You're the one who told me that
we were going to fight and that I should
go to trial. The second of the four
attorneys that came that day, a a true
southern gentleman, he said, "Listen, if
you were my own brother, I would beg you
to take this
deal." And I said, "But I I don't
believe that I've done anything wrong."
And then the third one, the one who I
liked and respected the
most said to me in a in a very perturbed
fashion, you know what your problem is?
Your problem is you think this is about
justice and it's not about justice. It's
about mitigating damage. Take the deal.
And so I said, "All right, if I don't
take the deal, what am I realistically
looking at?" And they said 12 to 18
years. And I said, 'All right, I have
five kids at
home. I'll take the deal. And and that
third attorney said, "This could be a
blip in your life or it could be the
defining event of your life. Make it the
blip." And so I took the deal. Did you
do the right thing? In retrospect, yes,
I did. It's so much easier to fight
these injustices from the comfort of
your own home than from a a prison cell.
Uh, you know, I I I wrote regularly when
I was in prison. I I didn't intend to.
Um, one of my attorneys said, "When you
feel comfortable once you get to prison,
send me a letter and I'll circulate it
to these 600 people who had signed up
for a mailing list just to see how I was
doing." So I waited about six weeks and
when I finally got my seal legs, I I
wrote something that I very arrogantly
called letter from Lorettto because I
wanted to model it on Martin Luther
King's letter from Birmingham jail. So I
called it letter from Lorettto and I
said two things. I said two strange
things happened to me. Well, one wasn't
strange. One was this I talked about an
abusive u just awful female prison
guard. But the other thing I said is one
of the other prisoners was walking me
around one day and he introduced me to
an Iraqi prisoner and so I saidalamu
alaykum may peace be upon you and he
responded and upon you peace and he
asked me where did you learn to speak
Arabic and I said oh I worked for the
CIA now I speak Arabic I love Arab
culture and history and poetry etc. And
then we shook hands and I
said, "It was nice to meet you." And I
walked away. The two days later, I get
called into the lieutenant's office and
I was told, "You never want to get
called into the lieutenant's office
because the likelihood is that you're
going to be sent to solitary confinement
because you've done something." So, I
hear my name being called to the
lieutenant's office and I go down there.
They have a picture of this prisoner on
a computer screen and one of the
officers said, "Do you know this this
man?" And I said, "I don't really know
him. I just met him a couple of days
ago." What did you say to him? I said,
"It's it's nice to meet you." And what
did he say to you? I said he said, "It's
nice to meet you, too." And then I shook
his hand and I walked away. And they
said, "Well, when you walked away, he he
made a call to Pakistan and he was told
to kill you." I said, "Come on. I could
kill this guy with my thumb." And they
said, "No, no, don't do that. just stay
away from him. I said, "Okay." So, over
the next couple of weeks, every time I'd
see this guy in the hall, I'd sort of
give him the the evil eye and he'd look
at me funny. But the more I thought
about this, the more it didn't make
sense. He was an Iraqi Kurd. Why would
he call a number in Pakistan where they
don't speak either Arabic or
Kurdish? And why would they tell him to
kill me? That doesn't make any sense.
So, I saw him in the yard and I went up
to him and he got a little scared and I
said, "No, no, no. I I don't mean you
any harm. I just want to ask you, after
we met in your cell, did the police say
anything about me?" And he said, "Yes,
they told me that after we met, you
called a Washington number and they told
you to kill me." And I said, "Oh, for
heaven's sake. Well, they told me you
called a Pakistani number and they told
you to kill me." and we got a a laugh
about how ham-handed this was. But then
I went to the to the law library and
looked this up and this was actually
class D felony. It was conspiracy to uh
promote violence in a federal
facility. And so I wrote about this
saying I've been here, you know, I was
there four days and already they're
trying to get me to kill a guy or to get
a guy to kill me for sport apparently.
Well, the blog went crazy because Ariana
Huffington picked it up and put it on
the Huffington Post. Then Jake Tapper
came to the prison to interview me and
The Economist came to interview me and
uh The Atlantic Magazine and CNN and it
was
ridiculous. And that was how I sort of
staked my position in in prison where I
have access to the media. I have a soap
box and I'm gonna make the best of it by
talking about prison conditions, medical
uh facilities in prison and uh and
violence that's encouraged by by the
guards and the administration. I drove
the warden crazy, but it was the right
thing to do. I had great access to the
media and it ended up being my second
book. Why did they not just stop you
from talking to the media? That is a
great question and it was one that
confused me for a little while and then
one of the other prisoners said that he
had overheard
um one of the guards ask the warden,
"Why don't you just send this guy to
solitary?" And the warden said, "Oh, so
I could have CNN standing in next to my
car in the parking lot tomorrow?" "No,
thank you." So I knew that was it. So
long as I didn't overstep. For example,
so long as I didn't name their names, I
was going to be safe. So, they were
afraid to cut you off from the media.
Yes, they were afraid. You could send
letters out. Did they read your mail?
They did. Not at first. At first, they
let everything go out. And then a couple
of people wrote to me saying, "Hey, your
last letter to me was very discreetly
cut on the side of the envelope and then
resealed with tape." So, I went to the
lieutenant's office boldly and I said,
"Hey guys, um, I've got a little bit of
um, intelligence best practices that I'd
like to pass to you. You don't need to
slit the side of the envelope open to
take the letter. What you do is you put
in a long
tong and you sort of hook the letter and
then you twist the tong so that the
letter turns into a little like a pixie
stick and you can pull it out of the
side of the envelope without acting
having to cut it open. I said, "Just so
you know, you morons." And then they
stopped cutting open my letters. H they
don't have the right to read your mail.
um they do legally, but uh policy in a
low security prison is to not read
outgoing mail, only to read incoming
mail. And really, it's not even to read
the mail so much as it is to check for
contraband.
So, they don't read outgoing mail
usually, but they were reading yours.
Correct. You think they stopped reading
it or do you think they started using
your technique? I I can't believe that
they were skilled enough to use my my
technique.
Let's cut to the chase. Your savings
could be in serious trouble. When Elon
Musk is out here warning us to brace for
temporary hardship, you might want to
listen. I trust Preserve Gold to
safeguard my accounts and I urge you to
do the same. They're the only precious
metals company I recommend. Are you
going to sit back and hope for the best
or take control of your financial
future? Text Dr. Phil to
50505 to get your free precious metals
guide from Preserve Gold. With gold
prices recently breaking records and
analysts predicting this trend to
continue through 2025, you cannot afford
to wait. As a bonus, you can get up to
$15,000 with a qualified purchase from
Preserve Gold. So don't wait. Text Dr.
Phil to
5050. That's D R P H I L
to505 today.
When it came right down to it, these
these guys, these lieutenants and and
they were called the
the something intelligence service, SIS,
oh, security and intelligence service.
These were not bad guys. They were just
in bad jobs. And I said to them, look, I
am no threat to you. I'm no threat to
your prison. I want you to know that
when I walked through those doors, I did
not lose my constitutional right to
freedom of of uh speech. But you should
really be spending your time on the gang
bangers and the pedophiles and the drug
dealers cuz your prison's full of them.
Don't waste your time on me. Were you
harassed in prison? Only by guards.
Never ever by prisoners. Never. And that
was for a couple of reasons. The guards
just have an attitude. There was a there
was a wonderful book published by Dr.
Peter Moscows. Uh he's a professor of
criminal justice at John J College and
um the book is called in defense of
flogging which is tongue and cheek. He
doesn't really defend flogging but he
said that the Bureau of Prisons is
really little more than a than an
employment agency for otherwise
unemployable
um undereducated rural white men. That's
why prisons are in the boondocks because
Prisons are the only industry in many
parts of the country. And so you're
going to get people who washed out of
the military or couldn't make it through
the uh through the local police academy
and they end up there. They're paid
hardly anything. Although the benefits
are good, they're federal benefits. So
you get people I I say this in my second
book, you get people who were probably
bullied as kids and sort of never got
over it. uh and this is their chance to
to bully somebody else, somebody who
can't defend himself, somebody who can't
fight back. You'll be you'll be accused
of insolence and you go straight to
solitary
confinement. So, I had problems only
with the guards, not with the the
prisoners. And I I do say also in in
this second book, Doing Time Like a Spy,
that on my first day, one of the guards
told me, and this is the only thing he
told me as he processed me in. He said,
"If someone comes into your cell
uninvited, that is an act of
aggression." And I said, "Oh, great.
I've been here 40 minutes and I'm going
to get my butt kicked." So, sure enough,
two guys came in. One had a swastika
tattooed on his neck. It took up the his
entire neck. Um, another one had white
power and swastikas on his arms. I
jumped up. I put up my my dukes and I
said, "What do you want?" And one of
them asked me, "Are you the new guy?" I
said, "Yeah, so." And he says, "Are you
a rat?" I said, "No, I'm not a rat." He
said, "Are you gay?" He didn't use the
word gay, though. And I said, "No, I'm
not gay." He said, "Are you a chomo?" I
said, "I don't know what that word
means." And he said, "Chomo, child
molester." I said, 'No, I'm not a child
molester. He said, ' Okay, you can sit
with the Aryans in the cafeteria.' I
said, 'Oh, great. Now I'm with the
Aryans of all
things. Uh, there was an Italian, and
when I say Italian, I mean named
Gambino, Banano, Lucesi, you know, you
get the idea. He read in the New York
Times that I was going to the prison. He
read in the New York Times on Sunday
that I was going to arrive at the prison
on Thursday. And God bless him, for
whatever reason, he took it upon himself
to go to every single Italian, including
the boss of one family and the acting
boss of another to explain to them the
difference between a CIA officer and an
FBI agent. He said, "FBI agents or cops.
CIA officers protected us from the
terrorists." And so when I arrived, the
Italians were waiting for me and they
welcomed me with open arms. And as soon
as word got around that I was with the
Italians, it was hands off. I never had
any problems. Really? Nothing. So where
did you sit in the lunchroom? I sat with
the Italians, I'm proud to say. Yeah. So
you didn't have to sit with the sounds I
didn't sit with the Arians. This all
sounds so absurd, but this is this is
life in prison. I I I also noted in one
of my blog posts that it's going into
prison is like walking into 1950s
America in that there is hard and fast
racial
segregation. Whites and blacks are
completely separated. Uh they they don't
eat together. They don't watch TV
together. They usually don't even room
together. And then the Hispanics are off
in their own area. So you have one table
that is Aryans. You have one table where
half is Italians and half is Native
Americans. All the other white tables
are just for pedophiles and uh and
informants, rats. And then the other 50%
of the cafeteria is uh is black. The
Hispanics sit in the back. It it was
bizarre. It took me weeks to get used to
this division of the races.
Was there violence in prison? Did you
see a lot of violence while you were
there? Almost none. There were in the
two years I was there, I saw three
fights. Two of them were over what to
watch on television, which again was
just preposterous that people would
fight over such a stupid thing. And then
once uh one of the Aryans called a white
guy a rat and the rat just whipped him,
but that was it. You know, most of these
people too, they they worked their way
down from a a maximum security
penitentiary to a medium to a low and
they didn't want to go back up to the
maximum. So, they were on their best
behavior. I think people are interested
to know whether or not
CIA is engaging
in monitoring,
investigating, looking at data of
American citizens. Yeah, that is such an
important question. We know for a fact
that both NSA and FBI definitely are and
they're doing it in such a a a terrible
way. This is something that really
requires a legislative fix. Um rather
than to go to a judge to ask for a
warrant. So rather than having to find
probable cause, they now just go to the
data providers and buy the data. It's
for sale. The metadata is for sale. It's
for sale by Facebook and X and and
Instagram and everybody. It just has it
for sale, so they just buy it. There's
no legal prohibition on purchasing it.
CIA is not supposed to collect any
information at all on American citizens
ever. Um, they say that they don't. I
want to believe that they don't, but I
really don't know. But they can go to
Meta and buy what? How would they buy
information on an American citizen? Can
they buy it in bulk or can they buy it
on an individual? How how do they do
that? It's far easier and more clearly
legal to buy it in bulk. Uh but then
they can sort through it and and pull
out your data. When you open an account
on Facebook, for example, or Instagram
or or LinkedIn or any of these social
media platforms, as part of the terms
and conditions, you agree that you're
turning over ownership of the metadata
to the company, and then they're free to
do with it whatever they want. Now they
most normally sell it to companies so
that they can target advertising to you
so that they can give you uh in your
feed advertisements they think that you
would react positively to but the
government will just take it to see what
kind of of uh articles you click on uh
what kind of comments you make. And I've
said too, well, not not that I'm unique,
a lot of people have said, you know,
they can figure
out whether you're calling your doctor
or maybe you belong to a depression
support group or an abortion survivors
support group or a a clean drug addicts
support group or whatever it is. They
can put a picture together of you based
on your metadata that doesn't really
require them to ever have to go to a
court and ask for permission to dig into
your past. Now, this is a new
phenomenon. It's just over the last 20
years and Congress just simply hasn't
addressed it. If you were going to go
back through your history,
what would you do different if you had
this to do all over again? Well, there's
one very important thing that I would do
differently, and that is I would have
hired an attorney before blowing the
whistle. Before I said a single word in
public, I should have had an attorney
sitting next to me and advising me. And
I didn't. And so, I had to be reactive.
You know, to tell you the truth, Human
Rights Watch had already said that the
CIA was torturing its prisoners. The
International Committee of the Red Cross
had already said the same thing. Amnesty
International had said the same thing.
So, I didn't think it was that big of a
deal for me to go out and confirm it. It
became a page one international
story. And having to be reactive to that
put me at a
disadvantage. I wish I had had an
attorney with me. What would that
attorney have told you that would have
changed what you had
done? What advice would that attorney
have given you now in retrospect that
you would have done something
differently?
The attorney probably would have not
told me to do anything substantively
differently other
than to not accept so many um press
requests, media requests. I should have
made the disclosure and that should have
been the end of it. But instead, I made
the disclosure and then gave 50 other uh
interviews. And of course, each
interviewer wants to build on the
original disclosure. And I was bumping
up against classified information. I had
to be very careful. And so, I'm just
giving the same interview over and over
and over. And then that kind of made
them angry because I wasn't giving them
a scoop. And then the criticism began.
And oh, it was it was not something a
person should try to handle on his or
her own. You should have a professional
doing it. Would you still have given the
original disclosure? Yes. Yes. Without
any question. Yes. Somebody had to say
something. We were committing a war
crime, a crime against humanity. And I
understand that, you know, we always
believed we were the good guys. I get
it. I still think we're the good guys,
but we were so traumatized by the 9/11
attacks. We so desired revenge against
al-Qaeda and against Osama bin Laden
that we just we just couldn't see that
line where we needed to stop, where we
would lose our sense of being Americans
were we to cross it. And you know,
another thing that I noticed is once we
crossed that
line, there was this effort internally
to just keep repeating the lie that it
was it was legal and it was justified
and it was ethical because if you repeat
that lie over and over and over again,
it becomes your
truth. And so I I figured, you know
what, I have to say over and over and
over again that it's wrong. It's wrong.
My my wife at the time gave me this
wonderful advice. She said, "You have to
keep talking about this because
eventually they're going to move on to
another issue or onto another person and
if you keep talking about it, your side
of the story is going to be the side of
record." And she was absolutely right.
And so I just kept repeating it. But as
you said, it was already out there.
People were talking about this. Yes.
There were all of these international
groups that were talking about it and
not just the other side. There were
credible groups that were talking about
what was happening. So why did you feel
the need to add to what was already
being said because they weren't being
listened to? Because there was denial
going on. Yeah, there was great denial
going on. uh the the CIA just flat out
denied there was anything even akin to a
torture program. And then President
Bush, and this is the reason why I gave
the interview, President Bush one day,
just a couple of days after Brian Ross
called me from ABC News, the president
gave a press conference in which he
looked right in the camera and said, "We
do not torture." And I said to my wife
who was a senior CIA officer, I said,
"He is just lying to the American
people." And then a couple of days
later, he's walking out of the South
Portico of the White House on his way to
the helicopter to fly to Camp David for
the weekend, and a reporter shouted a
question about torture, and he turned
around and said, "Well, if there is
torture, it's the result of a rogue CIA
officer." And I said to my my wife,
Brian Ross' source is at the White House
and they're going to try to pin this on
me that if it leaks, they're going to
say it was that guy. He was the rogue.
Kuryaku was the rogue. So I called Brian
Ross and I said, "I'll give you your
interview." And I decided that whatever
he was going to ask me, I was going to
tell the truth. Why did you think they
were going to pin it on you? Because the
the the program was falling apart. more
and more people were coming out and
saying, "Yeah, this was a mistake." And,
you know, these these human rights
organizations reports weren't based on,
you know, just a premonition that the
CIA was off somewhere uh torturing
prisoners. It was based on leaks from
the CIA. And I've seen this in the past.
I saw it during the the first Gulf War
where there's a major screw up and
people are killed and they need to pin
it on someone and that's what they do.
And I thought, "No, no, no, no. I was
the only one who objected internally.
The only one. I got passed over for
promotion because I objected to the
torture program. This is going to be my
issue. I'm going to tell the truth."
Okay. Now, tell me this. We all went
through this. We all went through 9/11.
I've said many times that I thought one
of the most important days in our
country's identity was
912 because on
912 we were all Americans. There weren't
any Democrats. There weren't any
Republicans. On the morning of 912, we
were all Americans and everybody came
together at that time. It was so tragic,
but Americans rallied and came together.
Obviously, they want answers from these
people. Who did this? And what's going
to happen next? What's the next thing
that's going to go down?
Now, there had to be
people in the
CIA, in the intelligence
community that absolutely
knew that the best way to get
information was not through torture.
This isn't a revelation that has come
about
after 9/11. I mean this has been known
for a long long time. This is not a new
revelation. Correct. You're absolutely
right. This we've known for generations
that torture doesn't work. And when you
were trained in CIA about how to do
intelligence gathering, the protocols
that you were trained
in, didn't they say and acknowledge that
the way to get
information was not through torture? Oh,
I'm so glad you brought that up. The
answer is a resounding yes. That is what
they trained us or how they trained us.
I remember being in the uh in the
operational training where we're we're
doing what's called the asset
acquisition cycle. Spot, assess,
develop, recruit. You spot somebody,
whether it's at a diplomatic cocktail
party or at a you know a riot or
wherever. You assess his um access to
information that you want. You develop
him by establishing a friendship or a
rapport and then you recruit him to be a
a source, an agent for the CIA. Well, I
remember asking specifically about the
use of threats. Do we threaten anybody?
You're going to work for me or I'm going
to, you know, pull your teeth out. And
they said absolutely never. First of
all, it's it's not ethical to do
something like that. Secondly, it never
works. And you run the risk of him
coming to the next meeting with a gun so
he can kill you for threatening him. So,
no, that never ever works. you you do it
by establishing a a bonafide friendship.
And I will add too that if there's one
thing that the FBI is exceptionally good
at, it is establishing that kind of a
relationship with a source. Ali Sufan
was the FBI agent who interrogated Abu
Zubeda at the secret site. He did such
an unbelievably great job that Abu Zuba,
having been given nothing more than a
piece of fruit, a cup of tea, a
cigarette, and a piece of paper and a
pen to write to his mother, just opened
up and gave Ali everything that he asked
for. Abu Zabeda gave us several things.
He gave us the al-Qaeda wiring diagram,
which we actually had never known. We we
knew that Osama bin Laden was at the
top. I'm Zawahi was the number two and
then we didn't have any idea below that
how the organization was configured. Abu
Zuba laid it out for us. Abu Zuba gave
us the um the modus operendi for an
al-Qaeda attack. For example, Ali would
ask, and I'm just making this up. This
is not real information, but this is
just what it was like. Ali would say,
"Well, if you were going to do an attack
in Dusseldorf, how would you do that?"
And Abu Zuba said, 'Well, I know I know
this man, Muhammad, and here's
Muhammad's cell phone number, and
Muhammad is a good planner, and he has a
cousin named Abdullah, and Abdullah has
weapons, and Abdullah has a roommate,
uh, and this is the address, and and the
roommate is named Rashid, and Rashid has
access to explosives. So then we could
go to the Germans and say, "Hey, listen.
You have a serious problem in
Dusseldorf. Here's the information." And
they could go and neutralize that
al-Qaeda cell. That was thanks to Abu
Zuba and it was thanks to Ali Sufan who
was able to to extract the information
from Abu Zuba using a very gentle touch.
Another thing that Abuza told us was the
name of of a brutal terrorist known to
us only by the
nomde. We knew that Mkhtar was a very
very bad man and we knew that this
Mkhtar had planned something called the
Bojinka operation. The Bojinka operation
was a plan in Manila, Philippines to
hijack
14747s at the same time and to fly them
into buildings all up and down the West
Coast of the United States. It was
foiled accidentally by a housekeeper who
went into this apartment being used as
an al-Qaeda safe house, recognized what
she was looking at as as a a potential
terrorist attack. She called the
Filipino police. They called the
Filipino Intelligence Service. They
called the CIA. And the thing was
foiled. But we didn't know who Mktar
was. And when Ali asked him, he laughed
and he said, "You don't know who Mktar
is? It's Khaled Shik Muhammad." We had
never heard that name before. And Khaled
Shik Muhammad turned out to be the
bonafide number three in al-Qaeda and
the head of al-Qaeda operations. Once we
had the name, we could target him. And
one year later, we captured him in Rahul
Pindi, Pakistan. And that operation was
called what?
Bojinka. B O J I N K A. Mhm.
And when was that supposed to happen?
1996, I believe it was. Wow.
See, we knew from 1996 onward that
al-Qaeda was planning to use aircraft as
weapons, but we just couldn't figure out
when and where they were going to do it.
How many 747s were they going to use? 14
of them. And how were they going to get
them? Apparently, the plan was to have
14 separate teams of hijackers. Now, it
was bad enough on 911 that they had
four. Can you imagine 14 crashing into
buildings in downtown Los Angeles and
and San Francisco and San Jose all the
way up to Seattle. A disaster of
historic proportions.
Unbelievable.
And it was foiled because a housekeeper
recognized something that didn't look
right. Exactly. We got lucky. Yeah.
Unbelievable. But the question that I
was getting to is they trained you. They
know because it's knowable that the best
way and even the fastest way even if
you're urgent, it's like we need this
right now. They still know the fastest
way to get the best information is not
through torture but through relationship
building. That's exactly right. Why
would they default to torture at that
time? And the reason I'm saying this is
because we know that when you
torture, you almost every time get a
piece of information,
but it's not quality information. You do
get something, but it's almost always
not reliable. They will give you
something to get you to stop in the
moment, and then you go spin your wheels
and check this, check that, check the
other. The most dangerous lie is that
with a kernel of truth, and they'll give
you something that has nothing of
substance, but it's enough to keep you
chasing your tail. You waste time and go
spend all this effort and energy and get
nowhere. And that is exactly No, you're
100% right. That is the the whole crux
of the issue. You have to devote a team
of analysts to to pour through this
information that was collected under
torture. It's going to take analysts
months months to get through this
information. And in the meantime, that
allows the terrorists months to plan
their next attack. So, it's it's just
terrible. But, you know, we we can't
underestimate the the role of of revenge
in in the CIA's torture program. There
were CIA leaders who had been so proud
of their careers, so proud of what they
had accomplished over the course of 20,
25, 30 years, thinking, "Oh my god, when
my obituary is written, they're going to
talk about my role in failing to prevent
9/11." And so there was this this
feeling that we had to do literally
anything to stop them. And even if it's
not to stop them, it's it's to pay them
back for what they did. When I finally
got assigned to uh Pakistan, uh and this
is just, you know, a couple of months
after the 9/11 attacks, I went back to
my home office um in the CIA's new
headquarters building. And um I told my
my immediate supervisor, I'm leaving for
Pakistan tomorrow, and I don't know how
long I'll be gone. It could be six
months. It could be a year. I just don't
know. And he leaned in and he whispered,
"Kill them all." And I remember saying,
"Really, John? Are we there
already? Kill them
all?" But that was that was the the
feeling in the halls of the CIA in the
in the weeks and months after 9/11. It
was payback time and that was really the
motivator for a lot of people.
So it wasn't necessarily to get
information, it was kick their ass. They
did what they did. So when you get one
of them, kick their ass. Kofheer Black,
who was the director of the CIA's
counterterrorism center, famously told
President Bush, and this was covered in
practically every p every paper in the
world, that when we got done with Osama
bin Laden, his head would be on a stick
and there would be flies on his
eyeballs. And that was the goal for a
lot of people. that didn't necessarily
make us safer. I mean, that's the thing
that I'm concerned about is where was
the goal to keep us safer. You're
absolutely right, Dr. Phil. It didn't
keep us safer. But, you know, the thing
the things that would have kept us safer
weren't weren't sexy from a policy
perspective. One of the things I learned
interrogating dozens and dozens of
al-Qaeda fighters was that they really
had no beef with the United
States. The United States was no big
deal to them. they were more concerned
about putting food on the table. And so
I always believed that if we had focused
on things like like education and
economic development where these people
could, you know, learn a trade, a skill
of some sort and have a job that would
that would pay them a few hundred a
month where they could get married and
and build a little house and and put
food on the table, we wouldn't have many
of these problems. Well, it may be that
simple. What's next for you? Well, you
know, I I'm proud to say that that
things have actually worked out uh for
me from a a personal perspective. The
the road has been a difficult one, a
long one. I I won't lie about that. Um
you really get to see who your friends
are and who your friends are not. and
they may surprise you, but um you know,
I've been invited to to uh to teach at a
variety of universities. I I have a an
intelligent studies class at the
University of Salamanca in Spain. Uh
it's at the graduate school level. I
lecture at the University of Southern
California each semester in the school
of journalism. Um I've got uh two
columns, one at Consortium News, one at
the Covert Action Magazine. I have two
uh podcasts. One is Deep Focus with John
Kiryaku. We look at these issues very
deeply. The other is called Deprogram.
And um and I've got a a little
internet-based TV show on unified
television called uh CIA Declassified
where we take documents, CIA documents
that the agency
declassifies and usually these documents
are 30, 40, 50 years old, but we use
them to explain important international
events like foreign military coups or
assassinations of foreign leaders or the
Berlin Wall or the Berlin airlift,
things like that. It's It's a lot of
fun. And you know, you have a little bit
here, a little bit there, and you can
put a decent living together. But with
that said, what I'm happiest about, what
I'm the most proud about is that my
children are proud of me. And someday
I'm going to be a grandfather. Um, I
hope that that for those generations of
my family not yet born, they'll be able
to look back on who I was and to be
proud. That's really what my goal has
been. Do you have
friends still in the service that you're
in contact with? I do actually. One told
me recently something that was very
funny. She said that
uh that she was taking part in a
security briefing and my picture was on
one of the one of the slides of the
briefing and it was entitled the insider
threat. And she said, "Everybody started
booing." And the instructor said, "What?
Why? Why are you booing?" And they said,
"He's not an insider threat. He was a
legitimate whistleblower." And in the
end, he was the one who was right. And
she said, "They've removed. They took
you off the slide from the security
briefing." Yeah. Well, I thank you for
plugging back in with me and talking
more about this. It's very insightful
and I hope we can stay in touch and
continue this dialogue. Every time I go
deeper, I get more and more questions
and thoughts in my head. And I think
you've been very educational for
everybody that's listening to you. I
wish you nothing but the best. I've
talked to a number of people that have
been in and are now out of the
intelligence community since my first
conversation with you because I have a
lot of friends in that arena. I haven't
found one person that had a negative
thing to say about you or the role that
you've played in all of this. And thank
you for the work that you're doing, Dr.
Phil, because it's so easy to sweep
these issues under the carpet. It's so
easy to let them just sort of dissipate
with time. So, I appreciate very much
that you're talking about these issues.
In my mind, these issues are not 20
years old. No, they're they're current.
We should be talking about them. Well,
they are current. We have to stay on top
of these sort of things and we should be
the most sophisticated country in the
world about this stuff and we should
conduct ourselves accordingly. I think
we need to be intelligence leaders in
this and we haven't always conducted
ourselves that way but I think we
certainly have the wherewithal to do so
and I think we should. I appreciate your
cander in all of this and again this
won't be our last conversation. You know
when I say that I pop back up so I
appreciate it. I'm glad. Thank you so
much. All right. Thank you so much.
We'll talk again soon.